Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
دعم الإدارة، شاهد على kissasia.cam أو kisskh.org
[The Vendetta of An]
[ثأر آن]
Your identity is no longer hidden.
لم تعد هويتك مخفية.
What do you mean to do with
ماذا تقصد أن تفعل بـ
those two disciples of yours?
هذان التلميذان اللذان تتبعهما؟
The fact that we are still alive
حقيقة أننا ما زلنا على قيد الحياة
is nothing but fortune.
إنها ليست سوى ثروة.
I trust you will not betray us.
أثق أنك لن تخوننا.
And that is because your children
وذلك لأن أطفالك
rest in the heavens,
ارقد بسلام في السماء،
watching over you.
أراقبك.
Someone kind crossed paths with you.
لقد صادفت شخصاً لطيفاً في طريقك.
They even set polished rice
بل إنهم يضعون الأرز المصقول
before an ownerless memorial tablet.
أمام لوحة تذكارية بلا مالك.
Chang'an
تشانغآن
is indeed a place of deep prosperity.
إنها بالفعل مكان يتمتع برخاء عميق.
We have reached the final brink.
لقد وصلنا إلى حافة الهاوية.
Soon children,
قريباً يا أطفال،
our answer will come soon.
سيأتي ردنا قريباً.
30 years have passed.
لقد مرت ثلاثون سنة.
When Chang'an falls,
عندما تسقط تشانغآن،
even in the winter,
حتى في فصل الشتاء،
the people of Tiemo will have
سيحظى سكان تيمو بـ
more grain than they could ever finish.
كمية من الحبوب تفوق قدرتهم على استهلاكها.
If only you could have been born in such times,
لو كان بإمكانك أن تولد في مثل هذه الأوقات،
how good that would have been.
كم كان ذلك سيكون رائعاً.
[Episode 22]
[الحلقة 22]
These past few days I have felt something is wrong.
خلال الأيام القليلة الماضية شعرت أن هناك خطباً ما.
Huai'an has not returned.
لم يعد هوايان.
Around the Taiyiji Clinic,
حول عيادة تاييجي،
there have been many unfamiliar faces.
لقد ظهرت وجوه كثيرة غير مألوفة.
All of this was arranged by you.
لقد رتبت أنت كل هذا.
Why?
لماذا؟
Master.
يتقن.
If you mean to kill me,
إذا كنت تنوي قتلي،
at least let me die knowing why.
على الأقل دعني أموت وأنا أعرف السبب.
It is a simple truth.
إنها حقيقة بسيطة.
The people of Tiemo have entered the city.
دخل سكان تيمو المدينة.
I am Tiemo as well.
أنا تيمو أيضاً.
Every Tiemo shadow guard in the city
كل حارس ظل تيمو في المدينة
is searching for Xie Huai'an.
يبحث عن شي هوايان.
He is capable,
إنه كفؤ،
and he vanished without a trace.
واختفى دون أن يترك أثراً.
Fortunately I have you two.
لحسن الحظ، أنتما الاثنان معي.
He has very few friends.
لديه عدد قليل جداً من الأصدقاء.
For your sake,
من أجل مصلحتك،
he would do anything foolish.
كان سيفعل أي شيء أحمق.
Xiaoqing's life is hanging by a thread.
حياة شياو تشينغ معلقة بخيط رفيع.
Do not resist.
لا تقاوم.
Take her away quickly,
خذوها بعيداً بسرعة.
and heal her wounds.
وشفاء جراحها.
Master.
يتقن.
Xiaoqing.
شياو تشينغ.
What happened to you?
ما حدث لك؟
It hurts.
إنه مؤلم.
Do not be afraid.
لا تخف.
I am here.
أنا هنا.
You can only return to the Taiyiji Clinic.
لا يمكنك العودة إلا إلى عيادة تاييجي.
There are many of our people on Xiaocaomen Street.
يوجد العديد من أبناء شعبنا في شارع شياوكاومين.
They will look after you both.
سيعتنون بكما كليكما.
Master.
يتقن.
Must it truly be this way?
هل يجب أن يكون الأمر هكذا حقاً؟
For the great cause of Tiemo,
من أجل قضية تيمو العظيمة،
the lives of a child or two taken in
أرواح طفل أو اثنين أُزهقت
are not worth much.
لا تساوي الكثير.
Xiaoqing.
شياو تشينغ.
Let us go home.
هيا بنا نعود إلى المنزل.
Hold on.
يتمسك.
We are almost at the clinic.
نحن على وشك الوصول إلى العيادة.
Do not worry.
لا تقلق.
I will heal you, I promise.
سأشفيك، أعدك بذلك.
The wounds can be mended.
يمكن التئام الجروح.
But what of the heart?
لكن ماذا عن القلب؟
I will kill him for you.
سأقتله من أجلك.
And Master?
وماذا عن السيد؟
Will you kill him too?
هل ستقتله أنت أيضاً؟
You collapsed before Gu Yu's grave.
انهارت أمام قبر غو يو.
Our people carried you back.
لقد حملكم رجالنا إلى الوطن.
How many days has it been?
كم يوماً مضى؟
Four days.
أربعة أيام.
The physician examined you.
قام الطبيب بفحصك.
He said you did not faint from injury
قال إنك لم تُغمى عليك بسبب الإصابة.
but fell asleep.
لكنه غلبه النعاس.
Four days.
أربعة أيام.
News of Gu Yu's death
نبأ وفاة غو يو
must have reached the north by now.
لا بد أنها وصلت إلى الشمال الآن.
The death of a general
وفاة جنرال
can shake an army's resolve.
يمكن أن يزعزع عزيمة الجيش.
The Baiwenhu Army
جيش بايوينهو
may not hold.
قد لا يكون ذلك صحيحاً.
Now that the Tiemo forces march south,
والآن بعد أن زحفت قوات تيمو جنوباً،
what of Chang'an
ماذا عن تشانغآن؟
as it stands today?
كما هو الحال اليوم؟
Yesterday,
أمس،
Tiemo troops breached the North Office.
تمكنت قوات تيمو من اختراق المكتب الشمالي.
The North Office
المكتب الشمالي
is only 1300 li from Chang'an.
تبعد مسافة 1300 لي فقط عن تشانغآن.
The Huben Army excels
يتفوق جيش هوبن
at gathering intelligence.
في جمع المعلومات الاستخباراتية.
Nothing that happens in Chang'an
لا شيء مما يحدث في تشانغآن
escapes your eyes.
يفلت من عينيك.
Tell me,
أخبرني،
my friends...
أصدقائي...
Are they all dead?
هل ماتوا جميعاً؟
I fear
أخشى
they may wish they were.
ربما يتمنون لو كانوا كذلك.
Good.
جيد.
If so,
إذا كان الأمر كذلك،
then they are still alive.
إذن فهم ما زالوا على قيد الحياة.
And if they live, there is hope.
وإذا نجوا، فهناك أمل.
My pageboy...
حامل الخاتم الخاص بي...
Where is he now?
أين هو الآن؟
You are...
أنت...
Have we met before?
هل سبق أن التقينا؟
The last time we met
آخر مرة التقينا فيها
was 15 years ago.
كان ذلك قبل 15 عاماً.
Back then you were a young prince
كنت حينها أميراً شاباً
of Chang'an,
من تشانغآن،
studying at the Grand Academy.
الدراسة في الأكاديمية الكبرى.
To escape your lessons,
للهروب من دروسك،
you often claimed to be ill.
كنت تدّعي المرض في كثير من الأحيان.
You are...
أنت...
After all these years,
بعد كل هذه السنوات،
there is something I have always wondered.
هناك شيء لطالما تساءلت عنه.
The gift I gave you...
الهدية التي قدمتها لك...
Did you ever use it?
هل سبق لك استخدامه؟
I have a gift for you.
لدي هدية لك.
Mentor.
مُرشِد.
Wu Zhongheng?
وو تشونغ هينغ؟
It is me.
أنا هو.
Who are you, truly?
من أنت حقاً؟
Xie Huai'an did not have time to tell you,
لم يكن لدى شي هوايان الوقت ليخبرك،
I suppose.
أفترض.
I am Tiemo.
أنا تيمو.
All of Chang'an speaks of Gu Yu's death.
جميع سكان تشانغآن يتحدثون عن وفاة غو يو.
Yes.
نعم.
I was the one who killed him.
أنا من قتله.
Do not be alarmed.
لا داعي للقلق.
I will not kill you.
لن أقتلك.
Let us sit,
فلنجلس،
and speak of old times.
ونتحدث عن الأيام الخوالي.
Come. Sit.
تعال. اجلس.
You...
أنت...
How long have you been hiding?
كم من الوقت وأنت مختبئ؟
More than 20 years.
أكثر من 20 عامًا.
I traveled across
سافرت عبر
your entire land,
أرضك بأكملها،
then spent a few more years
ثم أمضى بضع سنوات أخرى
building a reputation,
بناء سمعة طيبة،
befriending the powerful.
مصادقة الأقوياء.
Liu Ziwen, Yan Fengshan,
ليو زيوين، يان فنغشان
Grand Preceptor Cen Weizong,
المعلم الأكبر سين ويزونغ،
even your father
حتى والدك
were all friends of mine.
كانوا جميعاً أصدقائي.
During my years at the Grand Academy,
خلال سنوات دراستي في الأكاديمية الكبرى،
I saw for myself
رأيت ذلك بنفسي
the brightest talents of Chang'an.
ألمع المواهب في تشانغآن.
Xie Huai'an,
شيه هوايان,
Gu Yu,
غو يو,
and your elder brother,
وأخوك الأكبر،
Xiao Wuyang.
شياو ويانغ.
And you
وأنت
were the most timid of them all.
كانوا الأكثر خجلاً بينهم جميعاً.
You are not the first to say that about me.
لست أول من يقول ذلك عني.
Once,
مرة واحدة،
Yan Fengshan said the same thing.
قال يان فنغشان الشيء نفسه.
Do not pity yourself.
لا تشفق على نفسك.
Because it is precisely your timidity
لأن ذلك هو بالضبط خجلك
that makes you
هذا ما يجعلك
the ideal candidate for the throne.
المرشح المثالي للعرش.
Many who hold power think so.
كثير ممن يملكون السلطة يعتقدون ذلك.
And so do
وكذلك يفعلون
the faraway people of Tiemo,
سكان تيمو البعيدين،
those who serve at the altar on Mount Shiluoman.
أولئك الذين يخدمون عند المذبح على جبل شلومان.
You see,
هل ترى،
timidity can sometimes be
قد يكون الخجل أحيانًا
a means of survival.
وسيلة للبقاء.
It allows you to live
فهو يتيح لك العيش
far longer than most.
أطول بكثير من معظمها.
Take Gu Yu,
خذ غو يو،
a man who always charged to the front.
رجل كان يندفع دائماً إلى المقدمة.
Men like him only die first.
أمثاله يموتون أولاً.
By the way,
بالمناسبة،
was it
هل كان ذلك؟
Xie Huai'an's idea to send you away?
هل كانت فكرة شي هوايان هي إبعادك؟
You were born into the imperial line,
لقد ولدت في السلالة الإمبراطورية،
yet you scare so easily.
لكنك تخاف بسهولة شديدة.
Yan Fengshan kept you under his thumb for years.
لقد أبقى يان فنغشان عليك تحت سيطرته لسنوات.
The throne slipped from your grasp long ago.
لقد أفلت العرش من بين يديك منذ زمن بعيد.
But in the great city of Chang'an,
لكن في مدينة تشانغآن العظيمة،
he is hardly the only one
وهو ليس الوحيد.
who wants to become another Yan Fengshan.
من يريد أن يصبح يان فنغشان آخر؟
Whoever grows powerful
من يكتسب القوة
will try to control you.
سيحاولون السيطرة عليك.
And this truth
وهذه هي الحقيقة
is something Xie Huai'an certainly understands.
وهذا أمر يفهمه شي هوايان بالتأكيد.
He should have killed you the moment he had you
كان ينبغي عليه أن يقتلك في اللحظة التي أمسك بك فيها
under control.
تحت السيطرة.
If peace is what he wanted,
إذا كان السلام هو ما يريده،
your death
موتك
would have settled everything.
كان ذلك سيحل كل شيء.
He is more human
إنه أكثر إنسانية
than you or Yan Fengshan.
منك أو يان فنغشان.
Indeed.
بالفعل.
You threw snakes at him back then,
كنت ترمي عليه الثعابين حينها،
yet he can still call you a friend.
ومع ذلك، لا يزال بإمكانه أن يناديك صديقاً.
He truly has a kindness that serves him little.
إنه حقاً يتمتع بلطف لا يفيده كثيراً.
When I entered Chang'an,
عندما دخلت تشانغآن،
my first move against the Huben Army
خطوتي الأولى ضد جيش هوبن
was to give him a new face
كان الهدف هو منحه وجهاً جديداً
and a forged identity,
وهوية مزورة،
fooling everyone.
يخدع الجميع.
Even Yan Fengshan
حتى يان فنغشان
might never have guessed it.
ربما لم أكن لأتوقع ذلك أبداً.
What I did not expect
ما لم أتوقعه
was that this plan
هل كانت هذه هي الخطة؟
would be uncovered by the King of Tiemo.
سيكشف ملك تيمو عن ذلك.
Zhu Zhilong is Tiemo as well.
Zhu Zhilong هو Tiemo أيضًا.
It turns out
اتضح
they had infiltrated us
لقد تسللوا إلينا
long before we knew it.
قبل أن ندرك ذلك بوقت طويل.
(Watch on dramacool.club to support Admin)
(شاهدوا على dramacool.club لدعم الإدارة)
My poor friends, both of them.
يا لهما من صديقين مسكينين.
I want to go out.
أريد الخروج.
Do you know where you are?
هل تعرف أين أنت؟
Of course I do.
بالطبع أفعل.
This is my sister's home.
هذا منزل أختي.
The pear tree in the courtyard
شجرة الكمثرى في الفناء
was planted by her own hand.
زرعتها بيدها.
To me,
لي،
this is where the general lived
هذا هو المكان الذي كان يعيش فيه الجنرال
and where he died.
وأين توفي.
Perhaps people like us
ربما أشخاص مثلنا
are fated
مصيرهم محتوم
to choose in the midst of chaos
الاختيار وسط الفوضى
between vengeance
بين الانتقام
and duty to the realm.
والواجب تجاه المملكة.
You do not need to choose.
لستَ مضطراً للاختيار.
I have already given you my word.
لقد أعطيتك كلمتي بالفعل.
When the Tiemo are defeated,
عندما يتم هزيمة تيمو،
you may come to settle your debt with me at any time.
يمكنك القدوم لتسوية دينك معي في أي وقت.
And in doing so,
وبذلك،
you will honor the Huben Army
ستكرم جيش هوبن
and General Fengshan.
والجنرال فنغشان.
With the general gone,
بعد رحيل الجنرال،
the Huben I can command is limited.
إن قدرة Huben التي أستطيع التحكم بها محدودة.
But if you fight the Tiemo,
لكن إذا قاتلت تيمو،
I will help you.
سأساعدك.
For now,
في الوقت الراهن،
I need time to think.
أحتاج إلى وقت للتفكير.
I said
قلت
I want to go out for a walk.
أريد أن أخرج في نزهة.
Before he died, Yan Fengshan said
قال يان فنغشان قبل وفاته:
that the streets of Chang'an
أن شوارع تشانغآن
might offer a different view.
قد يقدم وجهة نظر مختلفة.
Then tomorrow,
ثم غداً،
walk around Chang'an.
تجول في مدينة تشانغآن.
Chang'an
تشانغآن
can be beautiful at times.
قد يكون جميلاً في بعض الأحيان.
Steamed buns.
كعكات مطهوة على البخار.
♪Snow falls all over Chang'an♪
♪يتساقط الثلج في جميع أنحاء تشانغآن♪
♪Who drifts farther and farther away♪
♪ من يبتعد أكثر فأكثر ♪
♪The moonlight flowing through my fingers♪
♪ضوء القمر يتدفق بين أصابعي♪
♪Cannot bring back your face♪
♪لا يمكن إعادة وجهك♪
Huai'an.
هوايان.
♪I am willing to burn like a blazing flame♪
أنا على استعداد للاحتراق كاللهب المتأجج
♪To exchange for the full moon in the human world♪
♪للمبادلة مع اكتمال القمر في عالم البشر♪
An army may fall to the last man.
قد يسقط الجيش حتى آخر رجل فيه.
But Chang'an
لكن تشانغآن
must not fall.
يجب ألا يسقط.
♪Who holds the chess and looks down upon the world♪
♪ من يمسك الشطرنج وينظر إلى العالم من أعلى؟ ♪
♪In laughter and conversation♪
♪في الضحك والحديث♪
♪The hidden blade is too obvious♪
♪الشفرة المخفية واضحة للغاية♪
♪Though far away, my thoughts remain♪
♪رغم بعد المسافة، تبقى أفكاري♪
♪Everything in the world is at our fingertips♪
♪كل شيء في العالم في متناول أيدينا♪
♪And I am waiting for the day the mist clears♪
♪وأنا أنتظر اليوم الذي ينقشع فيه الضباب♪
♪Snow falls all over Chang'an♪
♪يتساقط الثلج في جميع أنحاء تشانغآن♪
♪Who drifts farther and farther away♪
♪ من يبتعد أكثر فأكثر ♪
♪The moonlight flowing through my fingers♪
♪ضوء القمر يتدفق بين أصابعي♪
♪Cannot bring back your face♪
♪لا يمكن إعادة وجهك♪
♪Blood spreads across these years♪
♪تنتشر الدماء عبر هذه السنوات♪
♪I am willing to burn like a blazing flame♪
أنا على استعداد للاحتراق كاللهب المتأجج
♪To exchange for the full moon in the human world♪
♪للمبادلة مع اكتمال القمر في عالم البشر♪
This is Gu Yu's
هذا هو غو يو
battle report
تقرير المعركة
that he hid inside his body.
أنه أخفاه داخل جسده.
Once you read it,
بمجرد قراءتك له،
you will know where you must go.
ستعرف إلى أين يجب أن تذهب.
Right now my friends' fate is unknown
مصير أصدقائي مجهول في الوقت الحالي
and I have no one else to trust,
وليس لديّ أحد آخر أثق به،
so I can only leave it in your hands.
لذا لا يسعني إلا أن أترك الأمر بين يديك.
But if you have other plans,
لكن إذا كانت لديك خطط أخرى،
you are free to choose another path.
لك الحرية في اختيار مسار آخر.
But I fear that Chang'an
لكنني أخشى أن تشانغآن
can no longer be held.
لم يعد بالإمكان الاحتفاظ به.
I will deliver this
سأقوم بتسليم هذا
to where it must go.
إلى حيث يجب أن يذهب.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Is there any news of Xiao Wuyang?
هل من أخبار عن شياو وويانغ؟
There has been no word at all.
لم يصدر أي خبر على الإطلاق.
What are you planning to do?
ما الذي تخطط لفعله؟
You mean to head north.
تقصد التوجه شمالاً.
Gu Yu is dead.
مات غو يو.
I have no allies
ليس لدي حلفاء
left to rely on.
يُترك ليعتمد عليه.
The deposed emperor and Ye Zheng
الإمبراطور المخلوع ويي تشنغ
are both in their hands.
كلاهما في أيديهم.
The Tiemo people are waiting for me.
أهل تيمو ينتظرونني.
This is the only road left to me.
هذا هو الطريق الوحيد المتبقي لي.
I will go to the Tiemo,
سأذهب إلى تيمو،
and help them kill Xiao Wuyang.
وساعدهم في قتل شياو وويانغ.
In the imperial court,
في البلاط الإمبراطوري،
the ones the Tiemo fear most
أولئك الذين يخشاهم تيمو أكثر من غيرهم
are Yan Fengshan and Xiao Wuyang.
هما يان فنغشان وشياو ويانغ.
Now that Yan Fengshan is dead,
والآن بعد وفاة يان فنغشان،
our only chance
فرصتنا الوحيدة
lies with Xiao Wuyang.
يكمن مع شياو وويانغ.
You should go.
يجب أن تذهب.
And you
وأنت
had better not die.
من الأفضل ألا تموت.
You owe no life to the Tiemo.
لا تدين بحياة لـ"تيمو".
You owe it to General Fengshan.
أنت مدين بذلك للجنرال فنغشان.
I owe him nothing.
لا أدين له بشيء.
Go.
يذهب.
Take care.
يعتني.
Father.
أب.
I failed to protect my sister.
لقد فشلت في حماية أختي.
No one walks away
لا أحد يرحل
unscathed
لم يصب بأذى
after facing Yan Fengshan.
بعد مواجهة يان فنغشان.
You guarded her all these years
لقد حميتها طوال هذه السنوات
and did everything you could.
وفعلت كل ما في وسعك.
In the end,
في النهاية،
you even avenged her.
بل إنك انتقمت لها.
Do not be so hard on yourself.
لا تقسُ على نفسك كثيراً.
Seeing my son
رؤية ابني
so weak and worn
ضعيف ومتهالك
breaks my heart.
يحزنني ذلك.
A father
أب
always aches for his child.
يتألم دائماً لطفله.
Since you came to Chang'an,
منذ أن أتيت إلى تشانغآن،
you have already lost too much. (Watch on www.kisskh .ws to support Admin)
لقد خسرت الكثير بالفعل. (شاهد على www.kisskh.ws لدعم الإدارة)
Then take the red ribbon down.
ثم انزع الشريط الأحمر.
Father.
أب.
Though our family's vengeance is repaid,
رغم أن انتقام عائلتنا قد تم رده،
Chang'an
تشانغآن
is far from peaceful.
الوضع بعيد كل البعد عن السلام.
I waited all night.
انتظرت طوال الليل.
I only wished to tell you one thing, Father.
أردت فقط أن أخبرك بشيء واحد يا أبي.
The King of Tiemo has arrived in Chang'an.
وصل ملك تيمو إلى تشانغآن.
Then take the red ribbon down.
ثم انزع الشريط الأحمر.
Very well.
جيد جدا.
Everything is done.
تم إنجاز كل شيء.
Only then did I dare come before Your Majesty.
عندها فقط تجرأت على المثول أمام جلالتكم.
Xie Huai'an's friends
أصدقاء شي هوايان
can no longer escape.
لم يعد بإمكانه الهروب.
We need only wait for him to appear.
كل ما علينا فعله هو انتظار ظهوره.
White Hair entered Yan Fengshan's courtyard.
دخل ذو الشعر الأبيض فناء يان فنغشان.
I cannot tell whether he won or lost,
لا أستطيع أن أحدد ما إذا كان قد فاز أم خسر.
so I sent you in.
لذلك أرسلتك.
For that,
لذلك،
you had to kill the master you served for years.
كان عليك أن تقتل السيد الذي خدمته لسنوات.
Do you regret it?
هل تندم على ذلك؟
No.
لا.
I have only ever served one master with my life.
لم أخدم في حياتي إلا سيداً واحداً.
Yan Fengshan is dead.
يان فنغشان مات.
The Huben Army is no longer a threat.
لم يعد جيش هوبن يشكل تهديداً.
Gu Yu is dead as well.
غو يو مات أيضاً.
Our forces
قواتنا
can march straight into their empire's heartland.
بإمكانهم الزحف مباشرة إلى قلب إمبراطوريتهم.
Only one danger remains.
لم يتبق سوى خطر واحد.
Xiao Wuyang.
شياو ويانغ.
If he dies,
إذا مات،
Chang'an falls.
سقوط تشانغآن.
Xiao Wuyang stands alone now.
شياو وويانغ يقف وحيداً الآن.
This time,
هذه المرة،
if our plan is thorough,
إذا كانت خطتنا شاملة،
he will not survive.
لن ينجو.
I saw something like this once,
رأيت شيئاً كهذا مرة،
a man on the edge of death,
رجل على حافة الموت،
hanging high on a platform.
معلقًا عاليًا على منصة.
He was an ordinary man,
كان رجلاً عادياً،
yet he lived for seven days and nights.
ومع ذلك فقد عاش سبعة أيام وسبع ليال.
If someone ordinary
إذا كان شخص عاديًا
can fight so hard to survive,
يستطيع أن يقاتل بشدة من أجل البقاء،
what about the King of Death, Xiao Wuyang?
وماذا عن ملك الموت، شياو وويانغ؟
Yes.
نعم.
The noodles are here.
المعكرونة وصلت.
Chili oil noodles.
نودلز بزيت الفلفل الحار.
Scallions dipped in vinegar.
البصل الأخضر المنقوع في الخل.
It has been more than ten years.
لقد مرّ أكثر من عشر سنوات.
Sha,
شرب،
you still remember my favorite bite.
ما زلت تتذكر لقمة طعامي المفضلة.
Of course I do.
بالطبع أفعل.
If I ever forgot it,
إذا نسيته يوماً،
I would lose my head.
سأفقد صوابي.
Sha,
شرب،
Cen Pickles came by, didn't he?
مرّ سين بيكلز، أليس كذلك؟
No.
لا.
After the Liu clan was wiped out,
بعد إبادة عشيرة ليو،
Yan Fengshan purged Liu's faction,
قام يان فنغشان بتطهير فصيل ليو.
and he never showed himself again.
ولم يظهر نفسه مرة أخرى.
Does he still need
هل ما زال بحاجة
to hide from Yan Fengshan's blade?
للاختباء من نصل يان فنغشان؟
Don't you also…
ألا تفعل أنت أيضاً...
Don't you also hide from him?
ألا تختبئين منه أنتِ أيضاً؟
Unbelievable.
لا يصدق.
Sha,
شرب،
that you've survived this long with that temperament
أنك استطعت البقاء على قيد الحياة كل هذه المدة مع هذا المزاج
feels like a miracle to me.
أشعر وكأنها معجزة.
Eat while it's hot.
تناول الطعام وهو ساخن.
Sha,
شرب،
in this world,
في هذا العالم،
I have patience for very few people.
لا أملك الصبر إلا على عدد قليل جداً من الناس.
You are one of them.
أنت واحد منهم.
Cen Pickles is another.
سين بيكلز مثال آخر.
If he came to you,
إذا جاء إليك،
and you don't wish to tell me,
وأنت لا ترغب في إخباري،
or he forbade you to say,
أو منعك من قول،
it doesn't matter.
لا يهم.
Just pass on a message for me.
أوصل لي رسالة.
Tell him I have arrived in Chang'an.
أخبره أنني وصلت إلى تشانغآن.
And that I hope
وأتمنى ذلك
we are still friends.
ما زلنا أصدقاء.
Cen Pickles,
مخلل سين،
who is he?
من هو؟
A man surnamed Cen.
رجل يُدعى سين.
Twenty years ago,
قبل عشرين عاماً،
everyone knew his name.
كان الجميع يعرف اسمه.
The Grand Preceptor, Cen Weizong?
المعلم الأكبر، سين ويزونغ؟
He was a friend of His Majesty?
هل كان صديقاً لجلالة الملك؟
The founding emperor,
الإمبراطور المؤسس،
Liu Ziwen,
ليو زيوين,
the Grand Preceptor Cen Weizong,
المعلم الأكبر سين ويزونغ،
and the man just now,
والرجل الذي كان هنا قبل قليل،
when they were young,
عندما كانوا صغاراً،
often gathered here.
كثيراً ما يتجمعون هنا.
Yan Fengshan
يان فنغشان
would sometimes come along too.
وكان يأتي أحياناً أيضاً.
He was younger
كان أصغر سنا
than the rest of them.
أكثر من البقية.
And in their eyes,
وفي أعينهم،
the so-called General Fengshan
ما يسمى بالجنرال فنغشان
was just
كان الأمر كذلك
an inexperienced young man.
شاب عديم الخبرة.
An inexperienced young man?
شاب عديم الخبرة؟
Later,
لاحقاً،
didn't he rule the empire for over ten years?
ألم يحكم الإمبراطورية لأكثر من عشر سنوات؟
In your eyes,
في عينيك،
I am also
أنا أيضاً
an inexperienced young man, aren't I?
أنا شاب عديم الخبرة، أليس كذلك؟
You...
أنت...
You are not human.
أنت لست إنسانًا.
When I had nowhere left to go,
عندما لم يعد لدي مكان أذهب إليه،
the boss took me in.
استقبلني المدير.
Later,
لاحقاً،
I went outside the city to collect his body.
خرجت من المدينة لأجمع جثته.
He was crushed to death.
سُحق حتى الموت.
Not even beasts would do such a thing.
حتى الوحوش لا تفعل مثل هذا الشيء.
I remember the boss's kindness.
أتذكر لطف المدير.
But I was born a Tiemo man.
لكنني ولدت رجلاً من تيمو.
My life was not his to give.
لم تكن حياتي ملكاً له ليمنحها.
Can I have a bowl of noodles?
هل يمكنني الحصول على طبق من النودلز؟
Get out.
اخرج.
After more than ten years apart,
بعد أكثر من عشر سنوات من الفراق،
I meet you again.
أراك مجدداً.
This is Yang Chuhao's courtyard.
هذا فناء يانغ تشوهاو.
Why did you suddenly
لماذا فجأة
decide to sun his books?
هل يقرر تعريض كتبه لأشعة الشمس؟
In his study,
في دراسته،
there truly are many fine volumes.
هناك بالفعل العديد من المجلدات الرائعة.
I even found
حتى أنني وجدت
a travelogue written by a friend
رحلة كتبها صديق
from my youth.
منذ صغري.
Reading it
قراءته
was like seeing an old friend again.
كان الأمر أشبه برؤية صديق قديم مرة أخرى.
An old friend?
صديق قديم؟
Then I am also one of your old friends.
إذن فأنا أيضاً أحد أصدقائك القدامى.
Of course.
بالطبع.
Back at the Grand Academy I asked you,
عندما عدت إلى الأكاديمية الكبرى سألتك،
when you grew up,
عندما تكبر،
what kind of achievement you wished for.
ما نوع الإنجاز الذي كنت تتمنى تحقيقه؟
Do you remember?
هل تذكر؟
Of course I do.
بالطبع أفعل.
I asked you,
سألتك،
when you grew up,
عندما تكبر،
what kind of
أي نوع من
career you wished to build?
ما هي المهنة التي كنت ترغب في بنائها؟
In times of peace,
في أوقات السلم،
to aid a wise ruler.
لمساعدة حاكم حكيم.
And in times of chaos?
وماذا عن أوقات الفوضى؟
In times of chaos,
في أوقات الفوضى،
to kill every enemy.
لقتل كل عدو.
White Hair,
الشعر الأبيض،
have you come to kill me?
هل أتيت لتقتلني؟
Mentor,
مُرشِد،
these hands of a scholar
هذه أيدي عالم
now hold no iron, no blade.
لا تحمل الآن حديداً ولا نصلاً.
How could they possibly kill the King of Tiemo?
كيف يُعقل أن يقتلوا ملك تيمو؟
I came
لقد أتيت
to trade for my friend's life.
لأضحي بحياتي من أجل صديقي.
You say you came to save a friend,
تقول إنك جئت لإنقاذ صديق،
but I do not believe
لكنني لا أعتقد
you would surrender quietly.
ستستسلم بهدوء.
It has been over ten years,
لقد مرّ أكثر من عشر سنوات،
and your intellect is enough to chill the bones.
وذكاؤك كافٍ لإثارة الرعب في النفوس.
You killed Yan Fengshan with strategy,
لقد قتلت يان فنغشان بالاستراتيجية،
because you understood him.
لأنك فهمته.
White Hair,
الشعر الأبيض،
as for me,
أما أنا،
how well do you understand me?
ما مدى فهمك لي؟
♪Begonias wait for the spring swallows♪
♪تنتظر زهور البيجونيا طيور السنونو الربيعية♪
♪Warm sunlight lifts the curtains♪
♪أشعة الشمس الدافئة ترفع الستائر♪
♪You take your first steps in the corridor♪
♪تخطو خطواتك الأولى في الممر♪
♪Gentle breezes play with your soft hair♪
♪تداعب النسائم اللطيفة شعرك الناعم♪
♪Carefree and untroubled, you laugh at everything♪
♪متحرر من الهموم وغير مكترث، تضحك على كل شيء♪
♪Your babbling songs♪
♪أغانيك المرتعشة♪
♪Set the passing years free♪
♪ أطلق العنان للسنوات التي تمر ♪
♪In this world, paths twist and turn♪
♪في هذا العالم، تتشابك الدروب وتتغير♪
♪Night fades as day arrives♪
♪يتلاشى الليل مع بزوغ النهار♪
♪After the rain, the sky clears♪
♪بعد المطر، تصفو السماء♪
♪The heart's lamp burns on♪
♪مصباح القلب لا يزال مضاءً♪
♪With a will that moves stone and metal♪
♪بإرادةٍ تُحرّك الحجر والمعدن♪
♪Breaking through every barrier♪
♪تحطيم كل الحواجز♪
♪I am the mountain standing behind you♪
♪أنا الجبل الذي يقف خلفك♪
♪Steadfast in my vigil♪
♪ثابت في سهري♪
♪In this world, flowers bloom and wither♪
♪في هذا العالم، تزهر الأزهار وتذبل♪
♪Seas turn to fields♪
♪تتحول البحار إلى حقول♪
♪The waning moon will always wax again♪
♪القمر المتضائل سيعود دائمًا إلى الظهور♪
♪Do not grieve our parting♪
لا تحزنوا على فراقنا
♪My only wish is peace in the years ahead♪
♪أمنيتي الوحيدة هي السلام في السنوات القادمة♪
♪You are the loveliest memory I carry♪
أنتِ أجمل ذكرى أحملها في قلبي
♪From here on, worry not for me♪
♪من الآن فصاعدًا، لا تقلق عليّ♪